this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software hello everyone this is Felina
for software engineering radio and today
today I have on the show with me Adam
Barr Adam bar has worked as a programmer
and manager and Microsoft's for more
than 20 years and he's author of several
books about programming including find
the bug and proudly serving my corporate
masters welcome to the show Adam thank
you glad to be here this show today is
going to be about your latest book that
I've just rant with great interest
called the problem with software why
smart engineers write bad code and this
is of course also what the book is about
so can you tell me more about that what
what in your view is good code or bad
code and what distinguishes between the
two well it's a it's a problem in the
software industry if there really is no
idea of what good and bad code is except
much later if the code has bugs or it's
hard to modify so it would be nice if we
could figure out while writing the code
or soon after whether the code was going
to wind up being good or bad that would
save a lot of time but right now people
just think code is bad if it doesn't
look like the code they would personally
write but a lot of those guidelines are
based on their own experience and
they're very anecdotal so you get these
code review arguments which are just
about my coding style versus your coding
style and the reality is any code that
somebody just wrote probably looks fine
to them because they understand that
they still have the the mental model in
their head so these arguments about good
code are really about two people
debating something with very little
actual facts behind them and that's why
you get these disagreements over things
because there are ways that people try
to measure good code yeah you already
mentioned coding styles but they're
different tests as well the people used
to measure if code is good like
cyclomatic
complexity do you think that makes sense
is there a way to measure Co quality or
is this all there really there is
nothing that I've seen even something
like method lengths and what what's the
right number of lines of the method so
I've heard people say that almost any
any low positive number I've heard
somebody say oh that's too long if you
have ten lines of code that's too many
if you need a comment that's too many
you need to immediately split the
comment section into another method
Steve McConnell when he was writing code
complete actually studied empirical
research where he could find it and the
number he came up with I think was the
number he found I mean was about a
hundred lines is too long which of
course is I think it's way longer than
people are actually claiming now is too
long the problem is you start to split
your code into too many small methods
and it's hard to track the logic through
the code so there probably is a good
number for something like method length
but nobody really knows what it is and
if there was research on it people
probably wouldn't be aware of it
cyclomatic complexity is another one
it's probably good to look at your most
complex methods and figure out what's
going on but there may be valid reasons
why it's better to have the method be
complex and to split it up into a bunch
of smaller methods just essentially the
alternative so I think these metrics are
useful to give you code to give a second
look at but there's no real standard on
what's too complex what's too long that
sort of thing and the things we talked
about so far are all internal code
quality so you look at the code and you
see if it looks nicely but of course
there's also something like external
code quality does it even matter if the
code is badly structured if the tests
just run if we have enough tests and it
does what the user wants it to do yes it
absolutely matters everything when
people talk about code reviews good code
bad codes they're really try to
anticipate the future they're
essentially saying I think this code
will be hard to modify in the future
because it'll be hard to understand and
it's not readable that's really what
they're getting at and that's critically
important as I said before almost any
piece of code you can get working in
almost any language if it's just one
person working on it and they wrote it
last week they'll remember how it works
the real problem is in the future when
people modify it when it gets modified
to work out for some different purpose
which inevitably happens when people who
originally worked on the code or no
longer working on it Fred Brooks who was
a person who wrote or is a person who
wrote a lot of important articles about
software engineering made this
differentiation between a small piece of
software that a few people worked on for
a short period of time and a software
product which has worked on over the
years by different people the team would
change and it would be a bunch of
different components merge together and
really what are you talking about code
quality worried about the second one
when it's not the original authors when
you have multiple people working on it
or multiple groups field working on it
will they be able to understand it so
it's absolutely critical if the code be
readable understandable even if the
tests pass even if today it works fine
for the customers so I think what you
were saying is that for you the
definition of code quality is if code is
easily modifiable if it's easy to change
does that work yes if it's easy it's
easy to understand and change and the
reason people want to understand code
generally is to change it so yes it's to
me the most important thing is can it be
modified without breaking it
accidentally or just because it's too
complicated to to touch without without
something breaking now you already
mentioned this a bunch of times in the
interview so far that there's definitely
a difference between small teams working
on small products and big teams working
on big pieces of software and this is
also one of the topics that is quite
prevalent in your book is about how
people when they learn to program often
when they're teenagers just doing it
when they're in high school they really
get used to this one person development
team that's just them
can you talk a little bit more maybe
about your experience growing up and
what things you learned when you were
learning to program when you were
younger so that was exactly my
experience I taught myself to program
this is in the early 1980s so first in
Fortran and then in basic IBM PC basic
we had a very early IBM PC model so
you're writing very simple programs I
would write simple games and when it's
just you even a language like basic or
Fortran is slide because you understand
what's going on it turns out that in
retrospect for trotted basic are
terrible languages for large-scale
development they the versions back then
didn't have methods with parameters and
local variables and or if blocks we
could actually have a block of code
after an if very basic things now but
they didn't have them so you learned to
write what they call spaghetti code with
lots of go twos and global variables and
you thought it was fine you got it
working you were the only person working
on it I thought oh this is great and
then when you got to larger companies
and you had to work with other people
and design api's that work together you
didn't have any training you thought oh
I know everything about programming look
at this awesome game I wrote when I was
younger and unfortunately Microsoft was
when it started almost entirely
populated with people like that people
who had taught themselves to program on
their own and thought they knew
everything about programming and
although they were smart people and they
got things working eventually it caused
all kinds of grief because people really
didn't know how to work in large teams
and write software that was maintainable
yes so let's talk about those all kinds
of Greaves what are some of the bad
habits that you picked up when you
learned to program on your own that you
later had to unlearn as a professional
developer well the biggest thing
probably was just being able to design
an API so really think about I'm writing
this code but somebody else is going to
consume it for use because software
tends to be layered like that so I have
to make the API clean and understandable
not just what I think is a nice API to
provide but what would be a clear API
for them to call
to document it well and all that so I
just have to think really about I'm
writing this software not as a mental
challenge to myself but as part of this
group of components that are going to be
stitched together and I really do think
about the interfaces the other thing I
learned I had to learn eventually was
that people doing code reviews are not
there to be malicious they're not trying
to insult your or your intelligence
they're actually trying to make the code
better and understand it and I think
that's a little tricky again when you've
always been working by yourself or or in
small teams very small teams in school
that really taking criticism is always
difficult and a code review feels like
criticism but it's very important for
the overall quality both for making sure
you don't have problems with your code
and also for other people learning about
your code so I think if you could that
that part of something I talked about in
the book which is programmers need to be
a little humble they need to not think
they're the greatest programmer in the
world and unfortunately you get a lot of
people coming out of college thinking
they are awesome programmers because
they've been able to teach themselves to
program be successful in college with
those self-taught skills and when they
get to industry they're really not ready
to accept the more learning they need to
pick up the the other set of skills they
need to be a successful program or
working at a company on a on a large
software project yeah we will definitely
get back to the teamwork and the
humbleness later in the show but for now
I want to focus on the source code
itself a little bit more so one of the
tips you already gave was you have to if
you want it write maintainable code you
have to think an interface is what is a
good API structure how are people going
to use my source code that seems like an
amazing tip do you have any other
concrete tips how do you make code if
you start working in a team that your
teammates will will not hate well I
think the other thing you you need to
read a lot of code somebody who has been
an analogy to be a good cook you have to
eat a lot of food before you start
cooking for yourself it's the same thing
it's another benefit of code reviews you
need to read a lot of code you need to
appreciate other people's style realize
that your style may be different but
there's reasons why people write code
with other styles and so it's something
I talk about in the book that I I'm
hopeful that universities can start
exposing people to large code bases
exposing students to large code bases so
they could really understand how large
code is structured and as I said just
learn to appreciate that there's
different ways to to write code so when
you work on even in university working
on two or three people projects which is
better I did a lot of solo projects or
with two people but now I know a lot of
universities work on three or four
people projects but it's still it's one
semester it's it the code goes away once
you get the grade kind of thing and so
you still don't really learn to work in
large code bases and and you tend to
know the people you're working with
you've worked out to design yourself so
it's still basically a fairly simple
project compared to what you do in
industry yes so you say read a lot of
code that seems also good advice but how
would I go about this imagine I am a new
programmer and I wanna learn to read
code what would I do concretely like go
and get up and read a random project
are there specific strategies you could
recommend well this is this is actually
a huge thing that's changed since I was
learned teach myself to program so back
then there really just wasn't large code
available to read because there was no
internet and you could you I used to
read these books these basic basic micro
computer games books and they had to
list things they might have a four page
listing of the computer game and you'd
actually type it in and and that was
about to it's the biggest piece of code
you could see and then if it was still
pretty short you maybe have to modify it
a bit to get it working but now you have
open source and you have these projects
that you could read at least you could
make local modifications you could even
contribute back to so yes it's it's not
it's essentially go to github and start
reading code but you could pick some
component that you use or you're
interested in or some area of computing
that you're interested in but yes
essentially do that go on github go find
some open source repository and
something you're interested in and try
to understand it figure out if you can't
understand it what it is about the code
that makes it difficult to understand
probably contact the author if you have
questions because really when you come
to work in industry that's what you'll
be doing for the vast majority of the
time it's modifying existing code
fitting into existing systems not
writing greenfield projects these brand
new projects that you tend to do when
you're in college or working on your own
and you also said that if people start
reading source code to learn more they
should appreciate a lot of different
styles what are their Styles you were
talking about is this imperative or just
functional or different programming
languages or well there's that too of
course you could read different
languages people have this tendency to
learn one language and then decide they
can solve all problems in that one
language but now it's really it's it's
things like method legs how you name
variables how you name methods how many
comments you put in that sort of thing
that the things that even though they
don't directly necessarily affect the
functionality of this software when it's
compiled it might all wind up being the
same thing but for readability and
understandability they're very important
so it's just reading a code and thinking
huh it took me a while to actually
figure out what was going on here why is
that is it something in the way the code
was structured that made it hard to
understand or was it a lack of comments
or maybe it's just a complicated part of
the code that's a little tricky but is
there something that could have been
done differently in the code style to
make it easier to understand so learning
code at a young age has also told to bad
habits like one letter variable names
and I really recognize your story into
learning programming from my own it was
a little bit later it was in the 90s but
it was very similar I picked up lots and
lots of bad habits when I was a teenager
and I had to unlearn them when I was in
university and later when I was working
should we conclude that learning to
program by yourself is a bad idea or do
you think ultimately it's still a good
preparation for a computer science
degree in a university so overall it's
it's a good thing not a bad thing we
shouldn't recommend to people not for
cam in high school
that first of all it does get you
excited about programming even something
at the hour of code which is of course
very very very simplified but it gets
people excited about programming we're
adding hey I could be a programmer too
which is great so and then there's
there's this skill of just I have a
twenty line piece of code and I know
that my variables are correct at the
beginning and the wrong at the end of so
I've narrowed the bug down to this
little section of code and I have to
kind of walk through it in my mind and
in this very precise way sort of
simulate the computer in my mind this is
actually what my book finds a bug is
about if you don't mind me throwing in a
plug for that it's about close in code
reading so that's a very valuable skill
just be able to debug any kind of
software when it's not working it's very
useful so you do gain valuable skills
learn to program in high school but you
also pick up bad habits I think the main
thing I wish people knew is that you are
picking up bad habits this understanding
that short small pieces of code you
write yourself are very different from
what you write when you're a
professional programmer if they were
just aware of that okay this is fun but
there's this other level I think that
would help a lot but I think a lot of
times it's presented as oh wow you just
did this little program you're a
programmer now go out and have fun and
and I think other industries people are
more aware that if they put a bandaid on
their arm or not they're not a doctor
they still have to go to medical school
in programming that that distinction is
I think often lost and in in a lot of
ways people like me sort of pulled it
off for a while we we did teach ourself
to program we're successful in
University and and went off got jobs at
good companies and eventually realized
that we had a big skillset gap but after
much grief as I put it earlier you try
to figure it out and having two other
people have to deal with us and and so
on
yeah there's of course also the effect
and you mentioned this in your book as
well on on your classmates and and I
teach at a university of some people in
the audience might know so we get
freshmen in university some of these
eighteen year olds have never programmed
and they're welcome as well in the
university and other people in the same
classroom have like 10 years of
programming experience and sometimes
need in the age of github
this is serious programming experience
and those experienced students repel
some of the students that have less
experience that might be people from our
lower socioeconomic status where they
don't have access to lots of programming
tools or and this is something that you
mentioned in the book as well female
students often are like whoa those other
people in my class there are already
brilliant programmers for them the
band-aid I love this analogy the band
they people also look like like proper
surgeons how should we deal with that
right there's a great book called
unlocking the clubhouse which is
specifically about women getting scared
away from programming in university
because all these high school geeks seem
so confident and fluid at programming
and the quotes are really depressing
when you read them about how these women
are clearly very smart but they're just
to just feel like everything is so much
harder for them and it's this
insurmountable barrier and of course the
guys also have negative attitudes and
look down on them what are you doing in
the computer lab kind of thing so all
that contributes to make them decide to
switch majors I think that you certainly
want to make programming as welcoming as
possible to people if not programmed in
high school whether it's women as you
said different economic backgrounds or
there's all kinds of reasons why people
might not have been programmers in high
school and so it's it's tricky schools
have tried different things covers some
schools programming program they teach
their introductory classes in a
functional language like ml which is
strange enough that very few people will
have programs in it so that kind of
knocks the experienced programmers down
a few pegs schools also try to focus on
more interesting programming projects so
not just learning to program sorting
algorithms but actually doing something
through robotics or something with games
so the end result is more interesting
it's not just geeking out on code and
it's also things that have to happen
earlier
highschool in middle school so if
somebody's trying to get in student
programming asking questions taking a
program in class whatever it is they're
not looked at weird because they don't
fit the the stereotype of a program I
think it's just gonna be a very gradual
thing
more people are interested in
programming early which makes it less
strange which means more people wind up
majoring it which means there's more
role models to look at for younger
people I compared to something like
airline pilots airline pilots used to
all be male and it was a similar thing
I'm sure if a woman showed up at flight
school people would ask what she was
doing there or or try to order drinks or
something and just eventually through
more and more women becoming pilots it
became less strange and now she's
completely accepted that that women are
pilots but it took a long time to people
to get over it the other thing is
something that happened is old-school
airline pilots retired and retired
they're old-school attitudes along with
them and that'll eventually happen in
programming too but programming has
happened so fast
we've gone through this incredible cycle
in the industry and you still have
old-school programmers around who may
have old attitudes about female
programmers and it's gonna take some
time for them to retire because it's all
happened so fast compared to other
industries where it took centuries and
centuries for to gradually develop and
become important software has become
critical to the whole world in in 50
years yeah that's a good perspective the
the newness and the changing of
attitudes it still has to happen so
let's move on in education a little bit
because you talk in your book about how
you learn programming when you're in
high school but you also talk about your
experience in university quite a lot in
the book and so maybe you can summarize
that as well for the audience right so I
went to Princeton which is a good school
has a very good reputation very well
known computer science department and
what I found and I believe this is still
true since up until recently I worked at
Microsoft and I would have summer
interns and new hires out of college is
that universities tend to focus on
algorithms because that
what professors can can understand it's
it's very hard for professors also to
work on very large scale programs
because it's just one person and so they
tend to focus on on smaller programs and
and something you can really work on
well in a small program is an algorithm
so you learn sorting algorithms and
parsing algorithms and some of this
stuff is very important these days you
can work on artificial intelligence or
search or machine vision and those sorts
of things but you tend to learn that in
the classroom and the classroom is not a
computer lab it's just a lecture hall
and then you're told okay now go write
some code go implement this but you you
learn the actual software engineering
part more as a byproduct of having to
write this code that is something are
formally taught so people are rarely
taught how to structure codes or how to
debug code is very important skills that
you need a lot of when you're working
that I don't believe is is typically
taught in universities how to use the
debugger how to think about debugging
and again it's it's small pieces of code
so you're not learning how to write
large pieces of code you do have better
languages people tend to program in Java
these days instead of basic or Fortran
which is a better language it doesn't
have some of the fundamental issues that
languages did back then so so some
things are better but still you're
essentially even though you're going to
school and major in computer science or
software engineering you really kind of
teaching yourself to program you're
continuing that aspect of really
learning it yourself rather than being
taught it
why do you recommend it do you think
because the professor's told themselves
as well they think learning is easy so
I'm not really sure why I think I don't
think it's that I don't think it's that
oh well I I made it I'm tough I I did it
this way so I'm going to force everybody
else to suffer I don't think it's not no
I don't think professors I think that
way but I think it's partly that
algorithms is something that you can
learn what one person can really
understand an algorithmic area of
computer science and so it's probably
that
I think it's also just that industry is
it really expecting it so they're happy
to hire all the computer science majors
they can find so there's not really this
impetus to change because if you're if
you're thinking about I want people to
be employable when they graduate well
that's already happening and of course
universes are not entirely focused on
getting people employed ready to
graduate they're also interested in
research for its own sake and I think
they do tend to focus on things that
that one professor can do I wish there
was more empirical studies of large
software projects there used to be more
of that in the 1970s it's one of things
I talk about in my book is that they
used to be more research people actually
researched whether how bad go twos were
and commenting style and variable names
and indentation I mean all this stuff
was actually researched in the 70s by
academics and essentially what happened
is around that time the personal
computer revolution began people T
people could teach themselves to code at
home they did and they showed up at
University and they were sort of the
interest in that kind of empirical
studies dropped because people were just
already ready to code and they want to
learn new stuff and they had taught
themselves without studying historical
information about programming and they
just kind of continued along that path
well I do think there's some academic
research along those lines we had a show
about naming variables and I am myself
has done some research about how do
people name variables and they're quite
we can put some links in the show notes
people trying to measure ace camel cage
actually better than using underscores
and variable names there's some research
into eye tracking also I tracking and
code reading how people read code so
there's some of that empirical studies
happening now but that's that's great to
hear
III did not know about your research for
sure you can't you can't read every
everything you want to when writing a
book you just run out of time yeah there
there are still some empirical studies
there's an empirical studies journal in
conference it's still going on there so
no that's great to hear I wish there's a
lot more that I wish that students were
exposed to that to say oh wow there
actually is some some wisdom about this
it's not just my my personal experience
that could guide me but yeah I think a
lot of it the the human-computer
interaction studies the DAC my
conference which was started by our
empirical programmer studies people the
human-computer action rather than being
programmer to a computer interaction
which is kind of how it started out has
now turned into a user to computer
interaction so the the studies are more
about people using computers and
usability and all that and less about
programmers and your actual computers
but I'm very glad to hear you've been
studying variable in Haven and yes I'll
have to go read that relatively recent
the empirical software engineering
research has come up maybe in the last
decade right but of course it was also a
big thing 40 years ago so but if it's
coming back that that's awesome to hear
so you mentioned some of the skills that
we shoot yeah this is me as well we
should teach in universities for example
you mentioned debugging how to use a
debugger that's actually something
that's very important for students to
learn what other topics would you
recommend that universities teach
students apart from algorithms and stuff
like that well I I really wish they
would teach language choice so what is
an appropriate language for what sort of
problem there's a lot of talk about
functional programming these days and
functional programming has its uses but
people tend to be very binary on it the
other thing that functional programming
is terrible or it's going to solve every
problem in the world and really there's
some situations where it's good in some
situations where it's not or even a
language like Perl so Perl is a great
language for writing small pieces of
code per Perl is really great for that
small project short term quadrant where
you'd have to worry about long term
maintenance and it's the same people
always working on the software but then
you get
this evolved into these very large Perl
programs which are very hard to maintain
so something that's said that would say
okay for this kind of problem you can
use this kind of laying it was just kind
of problem you can use this kind of
language not necessarily teaching the
specific languages but just the general
concept that language selection is very
important and you shouldn't just use the
language you use for the last project or
the language you're most familiar with
because I understand in university it is
it's hard to learn a language so it's
convenient to say okay everyone will
learn Java and then we'll use Java for
everything or whatever language it is
but language choice is very important
thing for larger project so I wish there
was more focused on that as an actual
conscious choice you could make not just
a decision you slide into the others
actually some research into that is Wow
there was a guy called Leo Mayer off he
did a study I think among like 20,000
developers he interviewed them to this
to understand how they decided on which
language to use and the main factors
were not about language features the
most important things were two people on
my team know it and do we have
does it have libraries that we need
stuff like that and not even features of
the language this is definitely
something that if people decide to use a
certain language they are not
necessarily looking at features of the
language right there I think is of
course eventually if you're an
engineering discipline you would
hopefully you could decide that a
certain language or a certain code base
was obsolete so there's a lot of lot of
the current problems on the internet you
get exploits things like heartbleed or
whatever is is because a lot of the
internet tools are written in C a lot of
the fundamental internet software is
written in C which is a very bad
language to write Network facing string
manipulation code that's sort of like
the worst thing that C can do and that's
what it's used for a lot these days and
so if you could say you know this code
is just obsolete we need to replace it
we can't just keep using this stuff but
again because it's not really studied
that much and it works so hey why mess
with it
that's another area where I wish if we
were more of an engineering discipline
it's for a quota called software
engineering just as you can look at a
bridge and say that bridge is about to
collapse we need to replace it you could
look at a piece of software and say that
software is just not no longer
appropriate for what it's being used for
we need to replace it
but again people tend not to do that and
do you mean that at the level of a
repository or even as a language it's a
level of a programming language because
you've already mentioned a bunch of
languages in the interview saying like
Fortran is a terrible language and it
maybe shouldn't be used at all anymore
do you also propose we retire some
programming languages or is it more the
combination as you mentioned with C a
language plus an application that
shouldn't be used anymore yeah it's hard
to really retire programming language
because you have all this code that's
lying around it you keep hearing that
there's still a lot of COBOL programmers
out there and yeah there's still Fortran
and all that but yeah certainly to say
for new code given this criteria on what
it's being used for who's working on it
how it's going to be run what
environment etc this these languages
appropriate and these languages are not
and also a language like C has its uses
but I think that the the uses are
shrinking it the one of the things I
talk about a book is that this tends to
be a trade-off between clean design and
performance those two tend to fight each
other and language that our performance
focused like C and C++ are getting to be
borderline obsolete that the number of
cases where you actually care about
performance over clean design are
getting vanishingly small
even though old-school programmers who
taught themselves how to program on some
very underpowered personal computer
might still think that performance is
critically important than oh those kids
today don't understand what horrible
things they're causing to happen when
they write this Java string manipulation
code and everybody needs to go look at
their bytecode and whatnot I think
they're they're essentially wrong and
performance is almost never
problem and we should really focus on
the maintainability and clean design and
all that so a language a very
performance focus language like C or C++
really has almost no are useful
applications at this point and there of
course are also more modern languages
that focus on performance maybe
something like rust do you have an
opinion on that well I think that all
all languages that the big problem of C
was was was the string manipulation the
the using strings as arrays and the null
terminated strings which has caused vast
amounts of damage so even modern
languages they still tend to be better
designed they still can handle string
manipulation well so you could have a
more performance focused language but
what I'm talking about a lot of these
these old-school languages that were
really allows you to do to make mistakes
because it might if you didn't allow
that it might impact performance and so
I think it's really any modern languages
it's likely fine it's really these these
very old languages but they're still
around C and C++ microsoft has huge code
bases in C++ you know that's really
lingering from 20-30 years ago I know I
worked on such a codebase Microsoft also
managed to have some decent sized
programs in Perl as well a lot of the
tools are in Perl and that has its own
process with when you sit in large
software so it's not just old languages
but but I think again something like
pearls got useful in certain situations
but you need to be aware of when it when
the the benefits of Perl turned into
into negatives that the fact you can
call a method with any number of
parameters of course it's kind of nifty
for small pieces of code but turns out
to be a terrible idea for a large piece
of code now you mentioned some damage
done with C also in the book and this is
a story I didn't know about so I'm
hoping you could summarize it as well
for the listeners the famous Morris worm
was an early example of someone
accidentally making a huge mistake
with a C program could you summarize
right so the Morris worm was a buffer
overrun it was I guess probably the
first famous buffer overrun and see so
maybe there's a bunch of people out
there that aren't familiar with how C
handle strings which would be great
because the meaning that C was was dying
out but essentially C a string and C is
just an array and then the it's null
terminated so when you get to a
character 0 that indicates the end of
the string so the important thing is the
language is not tracking and C the
language the compiler does not track the
length of an array it's up to the
programmer to figure out how much memory
to allocate the store a string and they
have to count until they get to the
terminating 0 so this allows this
situation known as the buffer overrun so
the Morris worm was a buffer overrun in
network facing code so you could send it
network packet that was larger than
expected and it would actually overrun
memory and you could then jump into code
that was inside the pack and you sent
and take over the computer and the Moroz
were in particular called an api that it
used to exist in the c standard library
called get S which Molly did it use
strings which were null terminated so
they had this problem with allowing
buffer overruns but it was an API that
actually was passed me a string buffer
don't pass the length and I'll just
start copying data into it until I see
thee the end of a line so it was like
almost a guarantee like if you were
designing an API to allow a buffer
overrun that was exactly how you do it
so the fact that this API existed was
ridiculous and yet it was just part of
the C standard library the fact that
someone calls it a network facing code
was also ridiculous it was just an
exploit waiting to happen and yet when
it happened
the post-mortems were sort of like oh
well that that's a crazy situation why
would someone do that
we can't design perfectly secure
software so what are you going to do
because it was viewed as this weird
situation instead of the proper response
which should be hey maybe it's not a
good idea to
right all our internet software and see
but that was you know that that was it
that was the attitude back then if like
well yeah but you know it's it can run
faster and see so and that's cool I mean
uh think about performance is that you
you can it's easy to tell if something
is faster right even on a small piece of
software you could tweak the algorithm
and make it faster and and measure that
it's getting a little faster so people
get very excited about that and they can
see immediate results from from some
performance hack
whereas writing cleaner maintainable
code is sort of a longer term thing that
takes a while to realize if you've done
a good job you know we talk now about
performance performing languages like C
and C++ but what about the trade-off
between performance and readability in
general even within one programming
language because if I just I don't know
retrieve something from a database the
code will be really clean but if I use a
cache which might be more performance
the code will already be a little bit
more complicated because I have to check
if it's already in the cache and that I
get it from the cache and otherwise I
get it from the database so is there
always a trade-off between performance
and code quality well there almost
always this so I know it's nice to think
that that a cleaner algorithm is also
more efficient and and there
occasionally get something like that
where you really do something clever and
it's it's both shorter easier to read
and runs faster but in most cases yes
but performance is fighting against
cleanness Donald Knuth has this famous
quote that premature optimization is the
root of all evil to me I just say that
optimization is the root of all evil
almost all ugly code is because somebody
was trying to optimize for performance
now it doesn't mean you never do that
the original quote I think as money is
the root of all evil and it doesn't mean
that you should never have money it just
means that it causes other problems and
same thing with optimization you you
have a nice clean design and then you
say oh as you said we need a cache or we
need this sideband API so we can special
case this or we need some more
parameters to indicate this and it all
just complicates your design and makes
your
API is hard to understand and harder to
use and so in general essentially you
can always say don't do performance
optimization just as there's cases where
you might be in a car accident where you
get trapped by your seatbelt and for
some weird situation would have actually
been better not to have worn your
seatbelt that doesn't mean you don't
waste a Pell all the time because it's
generally better so there are cases
where you need performance optimization
sure but it's much better at a broad
level just to say no you don't need it
forget about performance optimization
just write your code cleanly and then if
it really turns out there's an actual
bottleneck that actually matters to
users then you could dig in and start to
make stuff uglier for performance
reasons but doing it because you just
think it's clever or it might be slow
I'm gonna do this little ugly hack for
performance is a bad idea and and and
unfortunate as I said I think a lot of
people still feel that oh no no
performance is critical and if you don't
understand the performance of your code
then you're a bad programmer and I
respectfully disagree yeah I think you
made really great points about the
measurability
that if you can measure it's quicker
then you get this immediate reward like
yeah I save 10 seconds where's clean
code it's just a longer reward so I can
I can totally feel how that is one of
the reasons that people tend to focus on
optimization because it just feels a
little bit like like a game or a puzzle
right even some of the coding standards
I've mentioned a book I once worked on
this piece of software or somebody
decided that all the header files this
is back in the C days all the header
files had to be alphabetized and order
in the program and which meant that we
had to do this complicated system that
basically any header file could include
any other header file because you never
know where it's gonna show up in order
and that's the kind of thing I'm sure it
felt great oh wow I got AB alphabetized
that that just looks so neat in the code
you know III it's like you know flossing
your teeth or something it just feels
good but I mean it really was was a
negative and yet you could do it and
feel like you were doing something
positive for the code and get like you
said this sort of immediate look how
neat that looks and maybe programmers
are a little bit prone to that because
they like to do clever things so you
have made some comparisons between
software and other things in this
interview and you also do that in the
book for example of course we talk about
software engineering and you have this
example of when we build a bridge and
one of the other metaphors you use which
also came up in the show is programming
as medicine that if you want to become a
doctor you need to have certification
you get in to say oh I open my own
butcher shop today do you want to have
an operation I can do it without any
certification those those things are
illegal and software is way different
where many people become programmers
they don't even have a degree in
computer science they just they haven't
agree to something else or there's
enough of a market pool where people
without a degree but with some talent or
interest can also get into programming
what are the effects of that well I
think that in one sense it's great the
we need programmers so if you can be a
music major and still be a good
programmer let's hire you but it's still
sort of weird that that works as you
said you don't have doctors who didn't
go to medical school now 200 years ago
you did have doctors who didn't go to
medical school they just follow a doctor
around for a while and kind of pick up
stuff and then it'd go off and and start
practicing medicine but eventually
people said no we don't want that yes it
might give us a few more doctors but
we'd rather have trustworthy medicine
instead and I think software may
eventually get to that point where
people really insist on some sort of
formal licensing for developers because
yeah right now you you hire somebody to
be a doctor I mean excuse me to be a
programmer and you really don't know
what you're getting it causes difficulty
in interviewing when companies are
trying to hire people somebody having a
computer science degree could mean all
sorts of things I'll say you I have to
put these programming question
interviews and stuff which are very
subjective there's no equivalent of
having a medical degree
and also just means that that there's no
standard to aim for universities don't
know a set of skills and knowledge that
they should be teaching that would match
what industry had decided was that the
proper skill set so it just caused a lot
of inefficiencies in the system right
now that you don't have any kind of
formal certification for something which
is becoming so critically important for
the world and unfortunately a lot of
security issues for example are
basically caused by the weakest link in
some long chain so you don't need your
software if it just says one one weak
spot you could have a security breach
and it might be that that one programmer
who didn't have proper security training
let's say who wrote that code and and
that's what let's he be exploited even
if the rest of your code is very solid
so it's very important that everybody
know what they're doing so why do you
reckon we don't have certification is it
because we're too young I think it's
because we're too young there have been
attempts at certification have been
attempts to publish bodies of knowledge
for for computer science or software
engineering but there's just not enough
agreement on what should be taught
there's this really this sort of gap
between industry and academia did I talk
about the book about they really don't
talk to each other about what we'd like
you to teach and and and and and what we
need when people graduate and how what's
missing from the academic side talking
to industry saying what he feels missing
in the people that are graduating but
yeah add right now if you look at some
of these bodies of knowledge it's just
sort of a long list of things people
have come up with about software but
it's nothing that's been been
demonstrated or
shown empirically to be the actual
skills you need and it's also kind of
too broad it's just a laundry list of
things about software and so you really
need to figure out the core the skill
set before you could actually start
licensing people and I think industry is
also worried
Computers software industry it's kind of
gotten away with not being liable for
software problems some of that is
probably fair because software is
complicated and and isn't as well
understood as other things but I think
also a industry's just saying well if we
have licensing that means we could be
sued if we don't hire licensed engineers
but also just has implication it okay
now there's licensing that means that
there's expected levels of quality that
would be produced by licensed engineers
and if we don't meet those we'll be more
open to lawsuits so I think there's that
particular issue is also it's causing
pushback from industry but I mean that
could be overcome you could just say
well that's great but we're still going
to have licensing but you'd have to set
it as a as a future target that
everybody worked towards not you
couldn't just impose it tomorrow because
there wouldn't be a correct body of
knowledge to actually license on so what
you're saying is what it would entail to
have such a certification is a deeper
understanding of what artists skills
needed to be a professional so for
engineers is that a good summary exactly
you need agreement between industry and
academia and also just more awareness of
what really matters and and what doesn't
matter what could be what needs to be
taught in school what could be learned
on the job that sort of thing because I
think industry industry is more
interested in people knowing specific
languages okay probably say oh well
every school should teach JavaScript
that would be great but but I don't
think that's necessarily true that's
just one specific language I'd rather
the university's focused on slowly
higher level of knowledge so right now
you'll be hard to get agreement on on
something like that so let's look at
current developments in the industry
then because your book you're saying
that you know we had bugs 40 years ago
30 years ago and basically we still have
lots of bugs do you think that the
software industry hasn't gotten any
better in terms of code quality well
it's gotten better I think that it it's
gotten better the language has gotten
better the tools have gotten better but
also the software being attempted
more complicated so I think we've we've
stated about the same point on the human
difficulty scale people are still
writing software that's slightly more
complicated than they they really should
be trying with their current tools of
the skill set which was true also sort
of throughout the history of software
engineering so yes there's a lot more
software and better software but you
still have problems because the software
is more complicated and people are more
are more dependent on if you look at the
history of software engineering which I
talked about in the book there's been
his search for quote unquote silver
bullets which is the from the from an
essay that Fred Brooks wrote called no
silver bullet and his point was there
will never be one magic solution to the
problems of software it's not going to
be only object-oriented programming or
unit testing or TDD or agile or DevOps
or functional programming or whatever
and yet people keep looking for this and
I think we're still on that train where
something new comes along like DevOps
and functional programming today and
everyone says oh finally this will solve
all the problems of software we could
forget about all that other stuff and
really those things are useful in
certain situations like all these other
previous silver bullets but they're not
a magic cure and people are still
looking for that magic cure and until we
can get past that and recognize it all
these things are useful
in their place we'll probably still be
stuck with people without really
thinking okay what how can we
fundamentally make software engineering
and the engineering no just keep chasing
the latest shiny object that promises
them a solution what do you think people
keep falling for those silver bullets I
mean we are allegedly all very smart
people well it's just it's just really
enticing to think wow if I just do this
one thing my problems will be solved I
think that the alternative which is okay
you just have to learn a lot more it's
kind of nice to be able to teach
yourself programming in high school and
they just have that carry you through a
successful career but that's not the way
it has to be in the future you're gonna
have to learn more in school you're
gonna have to learn more during your
professional career
Harlan Mills I think 40 years ago it was
a program worked at IBM and manager at
IBM and wrote a lot of insightful things
about software made a comment like that
the next generation of programmers is
just going to have to learn a lot more
and work a lot harder than the current
generation did because the the problems
are getting harder and so I think it's
nice to think that there's an easy
solution it's very tempting there's a
big industry out there as it is pushing
easy solutions or single solutions but I
don't think it's going to happen it did
software is just too complicated to have
one magic thing suddenly make it easy
but if there's no it's one magical thing
at least there must be something that we
can do right do you have any ideas how
we can improve
well what thing that's helping is the
move to the cloud because some of these
old wives tales about software are
actually now testable when you have to
maintain the software you have to
operate it keep it running rather than
just write it compile it and throw it to
your customers and let them deal with it
which was the way it was in the packaged
software days in the 90s you feel some
of the pain
of bad software immediately and you
realize oh wow this this software is
really hard to debug or this bug happen
because people didn't understand the
code or we had some test gap or or
whatever there's some process that
wasn't followed and so it's not a magic
solution either but it forces a little
more focus on quality because you feel
the pain more directly so hopefully the
move to the cloud will cause and is
causing some time we examination of what
quality software is and looking forward
if you talk about micro services and
auto scaling micro services hopefully
it'll put to rest some of this
performance concern as well this pre
optimization because if you have a micro
service that Auto scales you really have
to worry about performance except in
very rare cases and you could just make
a nice clean design let it scale as
needed in each individual service and
the performance things as I said it's
probably gonna happen but you see them
happen gradually your customer base
grows you see some looming performance
issue then maybe you could address it
then so I think the cloud pushes
software engineering in the right
direction even though again it's not
don't still be problems and software
will still be hard yeah because what
exactly is the role of the cloud there I
can have terrible software I'm put it on
the cloud and and still be terrible
right it's terrible but then you you
realize it's sooner because it's not
just like oh I got it cut a couple phone
calls from customers about our terrible
software it's it's wow my website
crashed and my database just fell over
and nobody could order anything and then
so you you you really realize like
you're losing money and you're losing
customers much more immediately when
it's cloud software then when it's
package software that that's running on
their computers so it has to do with the
feedback cycle being shorter
yeah the feedback cycles is shorter or
sort of immediate when it when it
crashes you realize it hopefully
immediately so yeah that does help a lot
just having that sort of feedback cycle
helps a lot with with pushing people to
care more about code quality which at
least it's a start maybe they don't know
exactly how to get to quality code but
at least they realize more than that
it's an issue you know and but one of
those people that a famous for pruning
stuff on the cloud actually seems to
have almost the opposite slogan because
Facebook famously says move fast and
break things it's not the opposite of
code quality if stop yeah I think I
think that's overstated a bit I know I
talked to people at Amazon since I live
in Seattle and and they do they wanted
to pull rapidly they sort of bias in
favor of shipping versus not shipping
but they also have very good rollback
tools and Amazon has such volume but a
company like Facebook ah so they can
just say okay our sales are down 10%
overall we just expect based on
historical data there must be a bug in
our latest deployment and they can roll
it back they don't even care what
happened they just know that if people
aren't clicking on the buy button as
much something is broken so they have
the volume where they could do that so
that allows them to buy us heavily
towards shipping because they also can
roll they could detect the need for
rollback very quickly and and most
companies don't have that scale so I
think the the this slogan about move
fast and break things it I think that
sounds great to people coming out of
college they want to hire but it's
really move fast and don't be super
concerned about breaking things it's not
a goal to actually break things as some
measure of of of positive activity it's
just because they could fix things
quickly they don't worry so much about
quote unquote breaking them yeah so it
has to do with the tools also maybe with
how much grip you have on what's going
on so let's talk about that a little bit
more because you already said before I
will notice if something is wrong
because my website crashes or my
database falls over but one of the other
examples benefits of putting stuff in
the cloud is you can have
automated tests and automates its
metrics and calculating everything even
before it breaks down do you think those
are the solutions or you should just let
it break or crash and then if we have
good tools to roll everything back and
we'll be fine well I mean of course
Amazon has company like Amazon has
multiple layers of detecting they're
looking at clicks it at the end but they
also have looking for API failures
internally and they have all these
metrics they look at to say okay well it
looks like something's wrong here and
and their their stuff is segmented into
services so they can deploy and rollback
individually so oh yeah no I mean so
it's a whole chain of things it's not
just put it out there and wait until the
users feel some pain because in the end
I mean somebody is not able to buy
something somebody's having a negative
experience if you let it get that far
even if you've only rolled it out to a
small percentage and and all that you're
still making somebody unhappy so yes you
want to check your internal testing
automated testing all these layers
before you you put it out I think that
so the nice thing that's happening now
is a lot of that is automated so you can
run through a bunch of testing very
quickly and deploy it you're not waiting
for a person to run through the website
manually and and make sure it works so
you can deploy it very quickly and very
frequently without having any extra
number of people involved in having the
human delay and possibly somebody not
doing a test exactly right and missing a
bug so so ya know it's it's a whole
chain of things not just throw it out
there and wait for errors god so do you
have examples of errors that you would
not be able to find in that way Dijkstra
famously said which is also in your book
is that testing can only show the
absence at the presence of errors and
not the absence so if we deploy stuff
how will we know about those things we
don't know about right well I mean in
the end yes you might you might have
some error that is in some esoteric case
that you don't find with your testing so
no doctors right I mean in the
you you if you find a bug you know it's
a bug but if you don't find anything it
just might because the bug is it's well
hidden but of course the more obscure it
is the less likely it is to hit so the
number of users affected is less so
you're here you might not have to roll
back for that maybe it's something you
can fix
and of course companies are investing
more and more and more automated testing
so doctor wasn't really thinking about
automated testing he was thinking about
manual user testing so that the scale of
what a test could do has grown a lot
since he wrote that but it's still true
I mean he wrote that in the 70s Harlan
Mills said the same thing in the 70s
despite that Microsoft rediscovered
testing in the 1980s and and spent 15
years relearning the fact that yes
you're right
testing doesn't find all bugs you can't
test in quality you need to work on
designing and quality it's it's sort of
a problem with the industry that because
people aren't looking back historically
they tend to spend a lot of time
reinventing things that were actually
already known if they had been been
paying attention I think that's a great
way to close your show because one of
the things you could do if you want to
pay more attention to the history of
software is is to read your book because
it has lots of great examples of old
bugs that that people might not be aware
of and strategies that have been tried
thanks a lot for being on the show is
there anything you wanted to add before
we close up no just to say thank you
very much for having me awesome so we'll
make sure we put a link to the book or
in the show notes do you have a website
are you in Twitter or our order places
where people come from I'm on Twitter
Adam David Barr I'll send you a link
I don't tweet a ton but it's it's a way
to get ahold of me
cool so with that in the show notes as
well thanks for being on the show yes
thank you thanks for listening to se
Radio an educational program brought to
you by Triple E software magazine for
more about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack channel at SC radio.com you
can also email us at team at SC - radio
net this and all other episodes of se
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening